Lothar Wolff collection, 1926-1987
George Eastman Museum
- Series 2, Film/TV Projects, 1932-1986
  - Subseries 21, Miscellaneous, ca. 1932; 1938; 1948-1967; 1973-1986; undated
    - no title (Box C301)
      - Sari Sapir, NOVA, WGBH, Boston, 1979 (Folder 67)
        Correspondence regarding the adaptation of "science material" from Eastern and Western Europe for PBS broadcast; background material on NOVA series.
      - TELECIP Script for "Worlds of Life,", undated (Folder 72)
      - Telepool/Hemmings, 1976 (Folder 73)
      - Donald Haynes,Wayne State University, 1981 (Folder 81)
        Brochure for proposed film "Workers ... Their Jobs, Their Union"; correspondence; UPS shipping record; handwritten notes; Mary Batten resume; "Workers and Their Jobs" film series outline, interviewee profile, "Film Specifications."
      - Richard L. Wormser:"The Life of the Party: The Rise, Decline, and Revival of the Communist Party, USA,", undated (Folder 84)
        Binder containing presentation for film project.
      - WQED"The Joy of Mozart,", 1976-1980 (Folder 86)
    - no title (Box C305)
      - "A Story of Bali" by Lothar Wolff, August 5, 1954 (Folder 1)
        "A Tale of Bali" written on folder. Script treatments/ideas for the proposed film.
      - Correspondence on "A Tale of Bali" --Vicki Baum, 1938; 1953-1962 (Folder 2)
        Correspondence regarding "A Tale of Bali", including correspondence with Louis de Rochemont Associates. Also includes 1938 New York Herald Tribune fiction "Tale of Bali" translated by Vicki Baum; budgets;Variety Dance Review; "Dancers of Bali" (undated); plot outline; blueprints [house layout?]; map of Bali.
      - "Tale of Bali" -- Outlines, 1957 (Folder 3)
        Outlines
      - Report on the Film Processing Laboratory, Sound Recording Studios, 1954 (Folder 4)
        "Containing 'The Tale of Bali'" written on folder. Laboratory and studio reports concerning "A Tale of Bali."
      - "Then and Now" -- A TV Series, 1979-1980 (Folder 5)
        Drafts, proposals, correspondence with persons including Allan Sloane, and articles related to "Then and Now."
      - "Then and Now" --Institut national de l'audiovisuel, 1979-1980 (Folder 6)
        Articles, brochures, and correspondence related to "Then and Now."
      - "Then and Now" -- Time/Life TV --Haidee Granger, 1979-1980 (Folder 7)
        Correspondence, clippings.
      - "Then and Now" --WQED Pittsburgh, 1980 (Folder 8)
        Outline of The March of Time material to be used in "Then and Now"; correspondence with WQED.
      - "Then and Now" --Nicole Jouve, 1980 (Folder 9)
        "Then and Now" material related to WQED Pittsburgh.
      - Where Are We Going To Put It?(Waste Disposal), 1971-1972 (Folder 24)
        Article clippings, PR statement from United States Atomic Energy Commission and the Mayor’s Office of Miami Beach, geological survey, and correspondence.
      - Hugh Gibb: "The Yangtze River" -- A Television Project, 1983-1984 (Folder 25)
        Project proposal and correspondence.
    - no title (Box C308)
      - Proposal for "The Glory of Bach" -- a one-hour TV special, 1985 (Folder 16)
        Proposal for an unproduced follow-up to The Joy of Bach[2 copies].
    - no title (Box C309)
      - List of March of Time Titles, 1980 (Folder 6)
        List of titles for possible use in "Then and Now" program.
    - no title (Box C310)
      - China in Change--The One Child Family-- Outline -- Script 1984, ca. 1983 (Folder 1)
        Outline of China in Change: Four 30-Minute Films on China, narrated by Glenda Jackson, produced by Helen Brew;China in Change English transcript.
      - Helen Brew--Media Insights Ltd., NZ --China in Change--The One Child Family, 1980-85 (Folder 2)
      - Helen Brew--Media Insights,The Foundations of Life, 1982 (Folder 3)
        Packet including "The Foundations of Life" background notes and related Media Insights correspondence [photocopy]; bound "Foundations of Life" materials, including proposal, script outlines, appendix, introduction.
      - Film Project on Asian Culture "The Japanese Films" by Froelich Rainey,University Museum, U. of Pennsylvania, 1977 (Folder 4)
        Correspondence regarding the "Japanese Films" (i.e.,Legacy for the Future, a 17-part archaeological documentary]; typewritten drafts of episode synopses ["The Mingling of Cultures," "Witnesses to the Past," "The Quest for the Colossal"]; English translations of episodes 16 ["The Summing Up"?] and 17 ["Epilogue"?] scripts.
      - [Binder labeled "Future Legacy Program Outlines"], 1975-1977 (Folder 5)
        Blue 3-ring binder with outlines of episodes 1-10 from Robeck Corporation; photocopy of 2/12/1977 Froelich Rainey letter; newspaper clippings about Mayan, Roman, Aztec, Syrian civilizations.
      - [Binder, "Future Legacy Episode Outlines"], ca. 1976 (Folder 6)
        Black binder labeled "Legacy" contains series episode outlines, "Additional Useful Materials." Inserted clippings about Bronze Age artifacts, damming the Euphrates River, the stained-glass windows at Chartres Cathedral.
      - Project on Jewish Holidays, ca. 1983 (Folder 7)
        Project outline: "In Celebration of Freedom: four prime time television specials"; Avraham Soltes resume; notes regarding Jewish Holiday Film Project; "Service for Sabbath Hanukkah" booklet; "The Passover Project" aka "A Question of Freedom" notes; newspaper clippings regarding Hanukkah, Jewish chapel at West Point; "The Cartoon Tycoon" promotional brochure.
      - Richard Thomas Fichter:Little Friend Project/Film, 1980 (Folder 8)
        Script draft with letter.
      - Look at the World-- Project by WQED Pittsburgh, 1976-1977 (Folder 9)
        Pressbooks; budget per subject; "Subjects under Consideration"; clipping regarding Buddhist shrines; letter regarding "Namib";The World About Us notes; letter from documentarian Hermann Schlenker.
      - Correspondence to Produce George Orwell’s 1984, 1954 (Folder 10)
        Correspondence regarding production of 1984, including letters to/from producer N.P. Rathvon, and mention of a possible Bach feature film;Time magazine,New York Times clippings reg Time arding production of 1984 film.
      - Fred Lawrence Guiles: "Norma Jean: The Life of Marilyn Monroe" a screenplay, ca. 1979 (Folder 11)
        Screenplay written by Guiles.
      - "The People of Asia" TV Series Planned?, 1969 (Folder 12)
        People of Asia series proposal in several drafts; preliminary budget; correspondence; memos; articles, publications, film catalogs, and other research materials related to Asia and its peoples; Barry Sloane resume; screening reports; list of possible subjects for "Other People, Other Places III."
      - "One Second before Sunrise" – A TV-series Produced by Horizon in assoc. w. Lothar Wolff Prod. and WDR, FRG, LAZI Film, FRG, 1986 (Folder 13)
        Bound report: "One Second before Sunrise: A Search for Solutions -- A Television Series" outline; shooting scripts, various drafts including final shooting script.
      - "One Second before Sunrise,", ca. 1983 (Folder 14)
        Script treatments, outline.
      - "One Second before Sunrise,", ca. 1984 (Folder 15)
        Treatments and outlines for episodes of "One Second Before Sunrise" series: "Just Beyond the Horizon: Water for the World (Working Title)" aka "Drop in the Bucket"; list of organizations, countries and individuals potentially contributing to the series; list of sources
      - "The Rescue,", ca. 1984 (Folder 16)
        Folder labeled "Preliminary drafts of scripts for a feature picture -- commissioned by Lutheran Film Associates-- about the rescue of the Jews in Denmark (by Danes) during the Nazi occupation of the country..." containing meeting notes, script changes, script draft.
      - [Binder labeled "''The Rescue' by Vee Wolff"], 1983 (Folder 17)
        Three-ring binder, also labeled "The Rescue 1983" on spine, contains script draft dated 2/5/1983; correspondence from Vera Wolff regarding script changes, script revisions; script changes, notations.
      - [Binder labeled "Rescue"], 1982 (Folder 18)
        Also labeled "'Rescue' Dec. 15, 82" on spine. Contains meeting notes regarding script changes [photocopy], script draft labeled "Second revise Dec. 15, 82."
      - Film Project on Romania, 1979 (Folder 19)
        Correspondence from Wolff about producing Romanian tourism films including outlines of project ideas; "The Best Kept Secret in Europe: A Film Proposal" by Patrick Nolan; magazine article about Romania by John Cheever; handwritten notes.
    - no title (Box C355)
      - Budgets -- National Geographic Society, 1979 (Folder 29)
    - no title (Box C367)
      - Copy from Lotte H. Eisner:Fritz Lang, NY, undated (Folder 1)
        Chapter 10 ("The Testament of Dr. Mabuse") and a partial Fritz Lang filmography photocopied from Eisner’s book Fritz Lang.
      - List of 16mm Prints of Lothar Wolff Prod., undated (Folder 17)
        List of 16mm prints of films produced/edited by Wolff.
      - On Mozart, 1977-1980 (Folder 18)
        Materials related to "The Magic of Mozart," an unproduced sequel to The Joy of Bach, including production proposals, correspondence, newspaper concert reviews, a concert program, arts brochures.
      - Newspaper Clippings for Frühlingsstimmen& Other Films by Fejos, ca. 1932 (Folder 21)
        Newspaper clippings, premiere announcements, and programs related to Wolff, Fejos, and films edited by Wolff in 1932-33, including Sonnenstrahl[aka Ray of Sunshine],Frühlingsstimmen,Le Roi des Palaces[aka King of the Ritz],Baroud,Rouletabille Aviateur, and Marie, a Hungarian Legend.
    - no title (Box C368)
      - Project: "Growing Up" and Letters, 1973-1975; 1979 (Folder 1)
        Clippings, various proposals, and correspondence.
      - [Unlabeled folder, "'I Shall Moulder Before I’ll Be Taken' -- 1976"], 1967; 1974-1976 (Folder 15)
        Red 3-ring binder containing clippings, script, footage list, interview transcripts, and narration.
      - [Newspaper Clippings, 1951-1966] (Folder 16)
        Clippings regarding Animal Farm, Indonesia,Johann Sebastian Bach, "A Living Church,"Windjammer,Question 7,The Challenge of Change,Fortress of Peace,Parlons Francais. Also includes correspondence with the Lutheran Laymen's Movement and NET Film Service, as well as pamphlets, programs, and photographs related to these projects. Materials in English and German.
    - no title (Box C371)
      - Planet Earth Revisited-- Interim Proposals/Reports, 1981 (Folder 12)
- Series 3, General Research Materials, 1947; 1957; 1967; 1972-1985; undated
  Series contains articles, clippings, correspondence, notes, outlines, script drafts, press materials, brochures, and other printed matter collected for research purposes but unrelated to any specific project. Dates range from 1947-1985, with the bulk dated between 1972 and 1985.
  Series materials are located in five boxes. If materials are dated, arrangement is in reverse chronological order.
  - no title (Box C301)
    - Articles, Letters Concerning Bronze age and Asian History, 1972-1976 (Folder 3)
      Correspondence, (including letters to and from the University Museum, U. of Pennsylvania); clippings regarding archeology; a Bronze Age archaeological dig in Ban-Chieng, Thailand; early Asian and North American civilization; paleontology.
    - Helen Brew(Filmmaker)The One Child Family,China in Change and PR Material for These Programs, 1984-1985 (Folder 10)
    - Granada International Productions(The Disappearing World), 1967 (Folder 20)
      The Disappearing World perfect-bound paperback book; press materials for series segments;Granada TV promotional brochure.
    - John Lutnes, Cameraman at Kitt Peak National Observatory, 1978 (Folder 37)
      Correspondence regarding astronomy films, including The Shoulders of Giants; astronomy film project outlines; magazine clippings related to astronomy; newspaper review of Journey into Light.
    - Nostalgia Channel,Ken Nimmer, 1983 (Folder 55)
      Nostalgia Channel press kit with popcorn and cover letter regarding National Geographic programming.
    - Polytel 76, undated (Folder 62)
      Press booklets for several Polytel International documentary TV series, including Marine Biology,Geographical Excursions,The Struggle for Survival.
    - James W. Prescott, Articles and Research, 1975-1979 (Folder 64)
      Correspondence; French journal article referencing "Rock-a-Bye Baby" with English translation; "The Futurist" journal article; "The Humanist" magazine article;Hustler magazine color insert.
    - Rudi Stern: "Let There Be Neon,", undated (Folder 69)
      Press and advertising materials about neon artist and his company.
  - no title (Box C308)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence Concerning The Joy of Bach, 1981 (Folder 7)
      Correspondence in English, French, German; letter from "Allan" to Thomas McDermott regarding Howard Hughes film project; production assistant resume; PRIMOB (Projected Image Mobile) 3D slide projection materials;Erwin Leiser bio; German magazine article on Berenice Abbott.
  - no title (Box C310)
    - Helen Brew--Media Insights Ltd., NZ --China in Change--The One Child Family, 1980-1985 (Folder 2)
    - [Binder labeled "Future Legacy Program Outlines"], 1975-1977 (Folder 5)
    - [Binder, "Future Legacy Episode Outlines"], ca. 1976 (Folder 6)
    - Look at the World-- Project by WQED Pittsburgh, 1976-1977 (Folder 9)
  - no title (Box C314)
    - Other People, Other Places Forgotten Wilderness, 1974 (Folder 8)
    - Antarctica Screening Report, 1982 (Folder 45)
      Photocopy of screening report.
  - no title (Box C367)
    - Manifesto and Program of the "Republican Union of Germany,", 1947 (Folder 3)
      Pamphlet
    - Booklets and Information on "The Nature Conservancy,", 1975-1977 (Folder 16)
      Annual reports, newsletter booklets, brochures, endangered species poster and newspaper clippings regarding private, non-profit conservation group.
    - Catalog of U.S. Government Produced Audio Visual Materials about: Space, weather, space programs, etc., ca. 1975 (Folder 34)
      Film-catalog entries excerpted from "U.S. Government Produced Audio Visual Materials," "The Educators Free Guide to Films,"NICEM (National Information Center for Educational Media) catalog,National Film Board of Canada.
    - Notes, 1975 (Folder 38)
      Notes regarding food and world hunger.
    - Articles on Natural Science, 1957; 1974; 1979-1982 (Folder 29a)
      Magazine articles, newspaper clippings, booklets, reports and notes in Wolff’s hand regarding geological surveyor Richard S. Williams Jr., astronomy, ancient history.
    - Articles on Natural Science, 1957; 1979-1981 (Folder 29b)
      Newspaper clippings, magazine articles, publications regarding the environment, physics, astronomy, geology, earth sciences, archeology. 1979 NASA Films catalog.
    - Articles on Natural Science, 1973-1982 (Folder 29c)
      Newspaper clippings, booklets, reports and papers regarding: earth sciences, astronomy; satellite image maps of Iceland.
  - no title (Box OS-1)
    - [Ballooning artwork and clippings], ca. 1984 (Folder 2)
      1980 Archaeology magazine article about ballooning; several pages removed from the book The Aeronauts(see Box C313, Folder 56)..
- Series 4, Festivals/Retrospectives, 1975-1986
  Consisting of 26 folders, this series includes correspondence, programs, photographs, newspaper articles, and festival/retrospective promotional materials dated 1975-1982 and 1984-1986. This series contains materials from film festivals with the bulk dedicated to Wolff’s speaking engagements at March of Time retrospectives, most notably a 1984 engagement in Japan. Of note, this series includes the script from Bosley Crowther’s introduction to a screening of a March of Time program on NDR German Public Television, as well as correspondence with Crowther.
  Series materials are located in three boxes, with the photographic material housed separately. Please see series "Photography" for more information.
  - no title (Box C300)
    - [Photo album labeled " 79/84 misc."], 1979-1984 (Folder 5)
      Photos taken during the March of Time retrospectives in Berlin (1979) and Tokyo (1984). Also includes a 1984 Japanese newspaper clipping regarding the Tokyo retrospective.
    - [Binder labeled " 79 Yorkton & Florence Film Festivals"], 1979 (Folder 6)
      Color and black-and-white photographs taken in Yorkton, Saskatchewan, and Florence, Italy. Includes photos of Wolff, actor Barry Morse.
  - no title (Box C301)
    - Hitchens, Gordon, 1977-1981 (Folder 26)
      Correspondence with March of Time retrospective host Gordon Hitchens. Essay "Die Gordon-Hitchens-Story" by Peter Ulbrich, April 1977.
    - Moritz de Hadeln, 1979 (Folder 33)
      Correspondence regarding earlier March of Time retrospective at Nyon film festival.
    - Donald M. Wilson, Vice President, Corporate and Public Affairs,Time Concerning Festival dei Popoli, Florence, 1979 (Folder 75)
  - no title (Box C309)
    - Introduction to Hand of Time, by Lothar Wolff, 1980 (Folder 2)
      The March of Time retrospective introduction dated Nov. 11, 1980.
    - The March of Time in Berlin, Arsenal, Frankfurt, Kommunales Kino, 1979 (Folder 4)
      Papers, newspaper articles, promotional materials, calendar. In German.
    - The March of Time Revisited -- Proposals, 1975 (Folder 7)
    - U. of Vermont -- Frank Manchel March of Time Screenings, 1976 (Folder 8)
      Screenings flyer and correspondence between Frank Manchel and Wolff, concerning a 1976 talk given by Wolff at University of Vermont.
    - Flashback(March of Time), 1984-1986 (Folder 10)
      Correspondence between Wolff and Flashback Television Ltd..
    - Prof. Reischauer "…and then Japan"March of Time, 1984 (Folder 11)
    - Ray Fielding (&March of Time), 1977-1978 (Folder 12)
    - Walker Art Center,Richard Peterson,The March of Time, 1978 (Folder 13)
      Correspondence and promotional material.
    - Japan/NAVL [Nippon Audio-Visual Library], 1984 (Folder 14)
      Correspondence (mostly between Nippon Audio-Visual Library and Time/Life), program notes, newsletters, and materials related to Wolff's speaking engagement in Japan. Materials are in English and Japanese.
    - Screenings in Vienna ( 1982 ), Programs, etc., 1981-1982 (Folder 15)
    - The March of Time-- Twelve Programs, ca. 1980 (Folder 16)
      Drafts, notes, and several complete copies of an outline for a 12-part retrospective titled "The March of Time: Twelve programs -- with discussion by Lothar Wolff, March of Time's Supervising Editor and Associate Producer -- spanning period 1935-1951."
    - Gordon Hitchens -- Research on March of Time, 1981-1982 (Folder 17)
      Correspondence with Gordon Hitchens; flyer for the Nippon Audio-Visual Library.
    - March of Time in Berlin, Frankfurt, Munchen ( 1979 ), correspondence with Enno Patalas,Ulrich George,Walter Schobert, 1978-1979 (Folder 18)
      Correspondence. Materials in English and German.
    - March of Time-- Introduction for Screening at NDR German Public Television, 1975 (Folder 19)
      Script from Bosley Crowther’s introduction (NDR-MOT Corporate Archives Version recording script) and correspondence with Crowther. Materials are in English and German.
  - no title (Box C352C)
    - [10th Festival International de Cinema Nyon Certificate], 1978
      Plastic and glass framed certificate presented to Wolff "en remerciement pour les services rendus comme member du jury international," October 1978.
  - no title (Box C367)
    - 10e Festival International de Cinema, Nyon, 1978. Letters, programs etc.Joy of Bach&March of Time[sic] (Folder 30)
      Programs, screening schedules, award lists, film synopses, press releases, tourism and hotel information, newspaper clippings, and correspondence regarding the 10th Festival International de Cinema, Nyon, 1978.
    - Festival dei Popoli -- Letters, etc., 1978-1982; 1985 (Folder 31)
      Programs, photographs, itinerary, and correspondence regarding the March of Time retrospective at the XX Festival dei Popoli, Florence, Italy, 1979, and others.
    - Margaret Mead Film Festival, 1978 (Folder 32)
      1978 Margaret Mead Film Festival programs, list of participants; speech text and correspondence regarding Wolff’s introductions to Festival screenings of Marie, a Hungarian Rhapsody and Medieval Moderns.
    - U.S. Industrial Film Festival Joy of Bach-- Gold Camera Award, 1982 (Folder 33)
      U.S. Industrial Film Festival Award Winner materials, including pamphlet, correspondence, and judging results.
    - Screenings: Nippon A-V Productions, 1984 (Folder 35)
      Correspondence with Nippon Audio-Visual Library (NAVL) regarding the March of Time retrospective, screening schedule, NAV (Nippon A-V Productions), and film programs with notes in Wolff’s hand.
    - Sheila Harris, Yorkton International Film Festival, 1977-1981 (Folder 39)
      Correspondence, brochures, programs, newspaper clippings, reports regarding 1977 and 1979 Yorkton International Film Festival, Yorkton, Saskatchewan, Canada.
- Series 5, Publications/Clippings, 1932-1946; 1951-1984
  Series consists of 18 folders, covering the date ranges of 1932-1946 and 1939-1984, and includes a variety of publications and newspaper/magazine clippings collected by Wolff and covering a range of topics. Materials include clippings related to film projects Wolff was involved in (generally not concerning the production, but articles published after the release), clippings made for personal reasons, and publications for which the purpose of his collecting is unknown. Many of these clippings and publications are related to topics frequently covered through Wolff’s career, such as the solar system and earth sciences.
  Series materials are located in four boxes. Some dated materials are in reverse chronological order.
  - no title (Box C301)
    - Theo Meier, 1983 (Folder 49)
    - John Phillips Yugoslavia, 1947-1948; 1977-1984 (Folder 59)
      Correspondence and articles regarding Life magazine photojournalist John Phillips and future TV projects based on his books Yugoslav Story and Jerusalem: A Will to Survive.
    - Tyrone Power, 1969 (Folder 63)
      Magazine and newspaper reviews of Tyrone Power biographies.
    - James W. Prescott, Articles and Research, 1975-1979 (Folder 64)
  - no title (Box C314)
    - Other People, Other Places – Screenings in London, 1974-1975 (Folder 12)
      Documentary film press materials; materials about alpine kiting; magazine article about poaching in African game preserves.
    - Copy of July 21, 1969 NYT with Moon Landing (Folder 39)
      New York Times July 21, 1969 issue; April 22, 1969 newspaper clipping about Wolff (unnamed in the article) tripping a diamond thief with an umbrella in New York City.
    - Several Copies of Image-- Channel 13/WNET Program Guide, 1971 (Folder 41)
      Four issues ( January-April 1971 ).
  - no title (Box C356)
    - [Album labeled "1. Berlin Prag 1927/31"], 1926-1931; 1979-1984 (Folder 4)
      Contains clippings from Film Kurier ca. 1930; an Er Und Seine Schwester/Meet the Sister press book; 8/7/1979 New York Times clipping about Brooks visiting George Eastman House; 6/15/1982 Variety review of Lulu in Hollywood by "Ever." (possibly William K. Everson); 5/1984 Films in Review article about Luis Trenker by Everson. Materials are in English and German.
    - [Album labeled "2.Mamsell Nitouche--Monsieur le Maréchal--Baroud--Poliche 1931/34"], 1931-1934; 1980-1981 (Folder 5)
      Article from Film Directions Issue 8.
    - [Album labeled "3. Budapest -- Vienna -- Cruise 12/33-1/34 "], 1932-1933 (Folder 6)
      Clippings include German newspaper articles about Paul Fejos, Wolff; 6/2/1933 article from Deutsche Film Schau headlined "Weisse Juden -- Die Grosse Gefahr"/"White Jews: The Great Danger." In German.